<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- comment -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-holmberg-dispatch-rfc7315-updates-02" updates="7315" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="7315 Updates">
		RFC 7315 Updates
	</title>
    <author fullname="Christer Holmberg" initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg">
        <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
                <city>Jorvas</city>
                <region></region>
                <code>02420</code>
                <country>Finland</country>
            </postal>
            <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
        </address>
    </author> 
    <author initials="N." surname="Biondic" fullname="Nevenka Biondic">
        <organization>Ericsson</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>Krapinska 45</street>
                <code>10002</code>
                <city>Zagreb</city>
                <country>Croatia</country>
            </postal>
            <email>nevenka.biondic@ericsson.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="G.S" surname="Salgueiro" fullname="Gonzalo Salgueiro">
        <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
        <address>
			<postal>
				<street>7200-12 Kit Creek Road</street>
				<city>Research Triangle Park</city>
				<region>NC</region>
				<code>27709</code>
				<country>US</country>
			</postal>
			<email>gsalguei@cisco.com</email>
		</address>
	</author>
	
    <date year="2015" />
    <area>Transport</area>
    <keyword>7315</keyword>
	<keyword>P-</keyword>
	<keyword>3GPP</keyword>
	<keyword>IMS</keyword>
    <abstract>
        <t>
            The 3rd-Generation Partnership Project 3GPP has identified cases where different 
            SIP private header extensions referred to as P- header fields, defined
            in RFC 7315, need to be included in SIP requests and responses currently not
            allowed according to RFC 7315. This document updates RFC 7315, in order to allow
            inclusion of the affected P- header fields in such requests and responses.
        </t>
        <t>
            In order to get a complete picture, this document also contains a set of errata 
            that are to be filed against RFC 7315, in order to fix misalignments that occurred
            when RFC 3455 was updated and obsoleted by RFC 7315.
        </t>
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
        <t>
            The 3rd-Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) has identified cases where different
            Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/> 
            private header extensions referred to as P- header fields, defined in RFC 7315 
            <xref target="RFC7315" pageno="false" format="default"/>, need to be included in SIP 
            requests and responses currently not allowed according to RFC 7315. This document updates 
            RFC 7315, in order to allow inclusion of the affected P- header fields 
            in such requests and responses.
        </t>
        <t>
            In order to get a complete picture, this document also contains a set of errata 
            that are to be filed against RFC 7315, in order to fix misalignments that occurred
            when RFC 3455 <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3455"/> was updated and 
            obsoleted by RFC 7315.
        </t>
        <t>
            This document updates RFC 7315 <xref target="RFC7315" pageno="false" 
            format="default"/>, by allowing the insertion of the
            P-Access-Network-Info header field in SIP ACK requests.
        </t>
        <t>
            As the P- header fields are mainly used in (and in most cases, only defined for) 
            networks defined by the 3rd-Generation Partnership Project (3GPP), where the updates
            defined in this document are already defined <xref target="TS.3GPP.24.229" 
            pageno="false" format="default"/>, the updates are not seen to cause backward 
            compatibility concerns.
        </t>
    </section>
		
    <section title="Conventions">
		<t>
			The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
			"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
			document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
		</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Errata to RFC 7315">
        <section title="General">
            <t>
                RFC 7315 contains contradicting statements regarding the 
                usage of SIP P- header fields in SIP requests and responses, which leave 
                the presence of the SIP P- header fields in the SIP requests and responses 
                open to interpretation, and different implementations. Statements in 
                section 5.7 are not aligned with the definitions and usage of the SIP P- 
                header fields specified in section 4.
            </t>
			<t>
                This section defines the errata that is to be submitted against RFC 7315. The scope
                of the errata is only alignment between RFC 3455 and RFC 7315.
            </t>
            <t>
                NOTE: In the case of the P-Called-Party-ID header field, allowing it in PUBLISH
                requests was deliberately done in RFC 7315. It will therefore not be impacted
                by the errata.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Correction to section 5.7 of RFC 7315">
            <t>
                The errata makes the following changes:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>
                        P-Associated-URI: Remove statement that the header field can 
                        appear in the SIP REGISTER method.
                    </t>
					<t>
                        P-Called-Party-ID: Delete statement that the header 
                        field can appear in SIP responses. Add statement that the P-Called-Party-ID 
                        header field can appear in the SIP REFER method.
					</t>
					<t>
                        P-Visited-Network-ID: Delete statement that the header 
                        field can appear in SIP responses. Add statement that the P-Visited-Network-ID 
                        header field cannot appear in the SIP NOTIFY, PRACK, INFO and UPDATE methods. 
					</t>
                    <t>
                        P-Access-Network-Info: Add statement that header field can appear in 
                        SIP responses.                     
                    </t>
					<t>
                        P-Charging-Vector: Add statement that the header field can appear in SIP 
                        responses. Add statement that the header field can not appear in the SIP ACK
                        method.
					</t>
                    <t>
                        P-Charging-Function-Addresses: Add statement that the P-Charging-Function-Addresses 
                        header field can appear in SIP responses.
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <figure>
				<artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                
Old text:

   The P-Associated-URI header field can appear in SIP REGISTER method
   and 2xx resonses.  The P-Called-Party-ID header field can appear in
   SIP INVITE, OPTIONS, PUBLISH, SUBSCRIBE, and MESSAGE methods and all
   responses.  The P-Visited-Network-ID header field can appear in all
   SIP methods except ACK, BYE, and CANCEL and all responses. The
   P-Access-Network-Info header field can appear in all SIP methods
   except ACK and CANCEL.  The P-Charging-Vector header field can appear
   in all SIP methods except CANCEL.  The P-Charging-Function-Addresses
   header field can appear in all SIP methods except ACK and CANCEL.
    

New text:

   The P-Associated-URI header field can appear in SIP REGISTER
   2xx responses. The P-Called-Party-ID header field can appear in
   SIP INVITE, OPTIONS, PUBLISH, REFER, SUBSCRIBE, and MESSAGE methods. 
   The P-Visited-Network-ID header field can appear in all SIP methods 
   except ACK, BYE, CANCEL, NOTIFY, PRACK, INFO and UPDATE. The 
   P-Access-Network-Info header field can appear in all SIP methods 
   and responses, except in ACK and CANCEL methods and CANCEL responses. 
   The P-Charging-Vector header field can appear in all SIP methods and 
   responses, except in ACK and CANCEL methods and CANCEL responses. 
   The P-Charging-Function-Addresses header field can appear in all 
   SIP methods and responses, except in ACK and CANCEL methods and 
   CANCEL responses.

				]]></artwork>
			</figure>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Update to RFC 7315">
        <section title="General">
			<t>
                This section updates section 5.7 of RFC 7315, based on requirements
                from 3GPP. This section contains the 3GPP use-cases behind the updates,
                and the suggested changes.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="3GPP Use-cases">
            <section title="P-Access-Network-Info">
                <t>
                    The P-Access-Network-Info header field may contain the Network 
                    provided Location information (NPLI). The Network Provided Location 
                    Information (NPLI) is described in 3GPP TS 23.228.
                </t>
                <t>
                    A proxy in possession of appropriate information about the access 
                    technology might insert a P-Access-Network-Info header field with its own 
                    values. Such values are identified by the string "network-provided" defined 
                    in RFC 7315. Based on operator policy and/or roaming 
                    agreement, local time of visited network may be included.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The CDRs generated within IMS have to contain the NPLI in order to 
                    guarantee correct billing. When an IMS Session is modified the NPLI also 
                    needs to be stored as the location of the user at the time when the 
                    session is modified may generate a charging event. In case of a session 
                    modification event at IMS, the NPLI needs to be provided:
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>
                            when the bearer establishment is triggered, or
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            at session release when the bearer deactivation is triggered, or
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            when the bearer modification is triggered e.g. QoS modification for the 
                            use of newly negotiated codec.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>
                    In some scenarios, the bearer modification may be triggered by the proxy 
                    upon reception of an SDP answer within SIP 2xx response to the SIP 
                    INVITE request. In such case the NPLI needs to be provided within the SIP 
                    ACK request. However, RFC 7315 does not allow the usage of 
                    the P-Access-Network-Info header field in SIP ACK request.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Upon reception of the SDP answer within SIP 2xx response on the 
                    SIP INVITE request a proxy may initiate procedures to obtain the NPLI and 
                    MAY include the P-Access-Network-Info header field with the NPLI in the 
                    SIP ACK request.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The P-Access-Network-Info header field shall not be included in SIP ACK
                    requests triggered by a 3xx-6xx response.                
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="P-Charging-Vector">
                <t>
                    RFC 7315 does not allow the usage of the P-Charging-Vector 
                    header field in SIP ACK request.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The P-Charging-Vector header field can appear in the SIP ACK request.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The P-Charging-Vector header field shall not be included in SIP ACK
                    requests triggered by a 3xx-6xx response.                
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Updates to section 5.7 of RFC 7315">
            <t>
                Note that the old text incorporates the fixes
                done by the errata described above.
            </t>
            <t>
                The following updates are done:
                <list style="symbols">
					<t>
                        P-Access-Network-Info: Add statement that the header field can appear in the SIP ACK method.
					</t>
					<t>
                        P-Charging-Vector: Add statement that the header field can appear in the SIP ACK method.
					</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <figure>
				<artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                
Old text:

   The P-Associated-URI header field can appear in SIP REGISTER
   2xx responses. The P-Called-Party-ID header field can appear in
   SIP INVITE, OPTIONS, PUBLISH, REFER, SUBSCRIBE, and MESSAGE methods. 
   The P-Visited-Network-ID header field can appear in all SIP methods 
   except ACK, BYE, CANCEL, NOTIFY, PRACK, INFO and UPDATE. The 
   P-Access-Network-Info header field can appear in all SIP methods 
   and responses, except in ACK and CANCEL methods and CANCEL responses. 
   The P-Charging-Vector header field can appear in all SIP methods and 
   responses, except in ACK and CANCEL methods and CANCEL responses. 
   The P-Charging-Function-Addresses header field can appear in all 
   SIP methods and responses, except in ACK and CANCEL methods and 
   CANCEL responses.
    
    
New text:

   The P-Associated-URI header field can appear in SIP REGISTER
   2xx responses. The P-Called-Party-ID header field can appear in
   SIP INVITE, OPTIONS, PUBLISH, REFER, SUBSCRIBE, and MESSAGE methods. 
   The P-Visited-Network-ID header field can appear in all SIP methods 
   except ACK, BYE, CANCEL, NOTIFY, PRACK, INFO and UPDATE. The 
   P-Access-Network-Info header field can appear in all SIP methods 
   and responses, except in CANCEL methods and CANCEL responses. 
   The P-Charging-Vector header field can appear in all SIP methods and 
   responses, except in CANCEL methods and CANCEL responses. The 
   P-Charging-Function-Addresses header field can appear in all 
   SIP methods and responses, except in ACK and CANCEL methods 
   and CANCEL responses.
                
				]]></artwork>
			</figure>
        </section>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Security Considerations">
		<t>
            The security considerations for the P-Access-Network-Info header field
            are defined in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC7315"/>.
            The update defined in this document does not impact the security
            considerations.
		</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="section.iana" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>
            This document makes no requests from IANA.
        </t>
	</section>
                   
	<section title="Acknowledgments">
		<t>
            TBD
		</t>
	</section>
		
	<section title="Change Log">	
		<t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]</t>
        <t>Changes from draft-holmberg-dispatch-rfc7315-updates-01
			<list style="symbols">
                <t>- Justification text for P-Access-Network-Info update added.</t>
			</list>
		</t>		
        <t>Changes from draft-holmberg-dispatch-rfc7315-updates-00
			<list style="symbols">
                <t>- Title corrected.</t>
			</list>
		</t>		
	</section>
</middle>

<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7315"?>
        <reference anchor="TS.3GPP.24.229">
			<front> 
				<title>
                    IP multimedia call control protocol based on Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)
                    and Session Description Protocol (SDP);Stage 3
                </title>
				<author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
				<date year="2015" month="September" day="25"/>
			</front> 
			<seriesInfo value="24.229 13.3.1" name="3GPP TS"/> 
			<format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/24229.htm"/> 
		</reference>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">	
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3455"?>				
	</references>
</back>
</rfc>